まかべ
(ケンジ)こちらＢ班 真壁です｡
パズルなんですけど➡
This is Makabe, from Team B.
About the puzzle...
It makes me uncomfortable to leave it unfinished.
完成させないと
何か気持ち悪いんで…➡
僕のだけ
後日回収でもいいですか？
てじま
Could you return my puzzle later?
What?
(ケンジ)よし｡
みぞぐち
(溝口)うまいですねえ 真壁さん｡
That's clever, Makabe.
自分の頑張りをアピールするのが｡
You're making yourself look like a hard worker.
下!?
From below?
なすだ
ほしか
(茄子田)おはよう 星加君｡➡
Good morning, Hoshika.
どうなの？みんなの様子は。
(星加)ええ ひどいもんですよ
茄子田さん｡➡
How's everyone looking?
Yeah, not too good, Nasuda.
全班 数値が荒れてます｡
会話にトゲが出てきてますし｡
(茄子田)あ そう｡
All the teams show signs of stress.
I see.
And they sound more agitated when they speak.
うんうん やっぱりね｡まあ10日も
経つとね こうなるんだよね｡
Yes, yes.
As I expected.
This is what happens after ten days.
それだけじゃないですから｡
あっ 何？
え もしかして…➡
That isn't all they have to deal with.
Oh, what?
Do you mean...
緑のアレ？
The green ones?
(福田)そうか 見られていたのか｡
I see...
So you were watching.
むった
(南波六太)ええ｡まだ誰にも
言ってません｡
Yes, I haven't told anyone else yet.
何で あんなことしたんですか？
Why did you do that?
さあ…何でだろうね｡
Yes, why indeed?
Huh?
もし君が その理由に気づいたら
その時は…➡
If you're able to figure out why I did what I did,
then when you do,
握手でもしよう｡
I'll shake your hand.
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
My goal is zero gravity
Space Brothers
Waves of people flood the intersection
Like vague silhouettes they stream past incessantly
How do I look in their midst?
I don't know
Hiding my true intentions desperately
I dish out vague excuses
My ambitions of going to space, harbored for so long,
are frail and brittle
No matter how I turn the globus
I have no home where I end up
There's no point to looking on a map
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
until I can look down on the entire world
I will yell
and scream
with a heart of steel
that I am going to zero gravity
#17 The Culprit Is in the Room
あ～ 何なんだ？この音…｡
(新田)うるせえな おい｡
What's that noise?
Keep it down, man!
どこで鳴ってるんだ？
Where is it coming from?
(せりか)あ～ 止まった｡
Oh, it stopped...
On our tenth night in the sealed box,
＜ここに入ってから
１０日目の夜のことだ＞
＜我々は ビービーうるせえ謎の
アラーム音に叩き起こされた＞
we were woken up by a loud beeping.
《今は多分…夜中の２時とか
３時とか…眠い》
It's probably 2 or 3 AM...
I'm tired.
何なんだ？
次から次へと｡
Why are we having so many issues?
《どうしよう…また問題が…➡
What should I do?
Now we have a new problem...
食料が足りないこと
さらに言い出せなくなった…》
This makes it harder for me to bring up the food shortage.
《でも いつかは気づかれるよね》
But eventually, they'll notice.
《そうなったら
この班はもう…》
When that happens, this team will...
Huh?
The camera?
《カメラ？…が どうした？》
Eh? What about it?
Let's find the source of the noise before going back to bed.
寝る前に音の出所を捜そうぜ｡
また鳴ったら うっとおしい｡
それも そうだ｡
I don't want to be woken up again.
That makes sense.
Where is it coming from?
どこにあるんだ？
《みんな気づかねえのかな…
やっさんの この不自然さに》
Has no one else noticed?
Something's up with Ya.
《右手は ず～っと
ポケットの中だし…➡
He hasn't taken his right hand out of his pocket.
そして何より変なのが…
さっきからコイツ静かすぎる》
And there's something else odd.
He's been way too quiet.
《本来なら アラームが鳴った時➡
I would've expected him to be the first to complain when the alarm went off.
まず一番に騒ぎ出すのは
やっさんのハズだ》
Who's making all that noise?!
⦅誰やねん！ピーピー
うるさい奴！南波か 南波！⦆
Is it you, Nanba? Eh?
Cut it out, Nanba!
⦅南波！ええ加減に
せえっちゅうねん!!⦆
That would've been the normal reaction.
《…と くるのが自然｡
ところが そうじゃなかった｡➡
But that isn't what happened.
Which probably means...
これは おそらく…》
《犯人を知っているか もしくは
やっさんが犯人か…➡
Either he knows who's responsible,
or he's responsible,
あるいは痔が痛むか…の
どれかだ！》
or his hemorrhoids are killing him.
Yes, must be one of the above.
何で ないんだよ｡
Why can't we find it?
全部見た？
Did you look everywhere?
Yes.
I don't see anything.
ないねえ｡
ないです｡
There's nothing here...
もう いいんじゃない？
寝ようか みんな｡
That should be good enough.
Let's go back to sleep.
It may well end up time for our morning call with Mission Control if we keep searching.
確かに捜してる間に 管制から
モーニングコールがきそうだしな｡
いや もう少し捜そう｡
気になる｡
No, we should keep looking.
It really bugs me.
What?
《くっそ～ 新田め…｡寝る前に
ゴキブリとか見つけたら➡
Stupid Nitta!
If he spotted a cockroach right before bedtime, I bet he wouldn't sleep until it was dead.
殺すまで眠れないタイプだな｡
コノヤロウ！》
しょうがねえ…
ちょっと顔洗ってくる｡
Fine, then.
I'll go wash my face...
I'm guessing that
《さっきの…あの福田さんの
目配せの意味は 多分…》
Fukuda was trying to tell me...
Look at the camera.
(福田)⦅カメラを見ろ…｡➡
Don't forget that we're always being monitored.
私達がずっと見られていることを
忘れるな｡➡
Do you think I would ruin my own chances with Mission Control watching?
私が管制の見ている前で
自ら夢を壊すようなマネを➡
すると思うかい？⦆
《思わないよ…》
I don't...
《最初はストレスで 気が変に
なっちゃったのかと思ったけど｡➡
At first, I wondered if he'd snapped from all the stress.
今は思わない｡
福田さんを信じよう》
But I've moved beyond that.
I'm going to trust Fukuda!
Hmm?
トイレや｡
Huh?
Restroom.
I'll trust him, too!
《あいつも信じよう｡
ついでに…》
Might as well.
Which means...
《となると…やっぱりこれは
ＪＡＸＡの演出…➡
JAXA must have had a hand in what's been happening.
Huh? What was that?
あれ？なんつったっけ？
こういうの…誰かに聞いたなあ➡
I remember someone mentioning something about this before.
え～っとぉ…》
Uh...
Hmm?
ジェニファー！
Jennifer!
⦅レゴリスっていう
尖った砂がね➡
Regolith, the lunar dust,
目とか肺とかに
ザクザク入るわけよ⦆
⦅なるほど⦆
had damaged his lungs and eyes.
I see...
⦅あっ ほら モニター見て⦆
⦅ん？⦆
Oh, look at the monitor.
Hmm?
ひびと
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](南波日々人)⦅あれ…？⦆
⦅ヒビト ピーンチ！⦆
Huh?
Hibito's in trouble!
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]⦅ちょっと…あれ？所定位置に
吸引ノズルがないんだけど…➡
Wait? What?
The suction nozzle's missing from its designated place?
ど～なってんだ？
ダミアン 元に戻してね～の？⦆
What's going on?
Damian, didn't you put it back?
Er, I can't remember...
⦅さあ…どうだったかなあ？⦆
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]⦅何それ？あ～！結構な
ﾀｲﾑﾛｽだよ これ…あれ？⦆
What's up with that?
Man, I'm wasting so much time...
Huh?
⦅ムッタ これね…わざとなのよ⦆
Mutta, this is all staged.
⦅ダミアンに グリーンカードが
出てんのよ⦆
Damian received a green card.
⦅ん？アメリカの永住権の？⦆
Hmm? Permanent resident status?
⦅いや それとは違って
ＮＡＳＡじゃ昔から訓練中に➡
No...
Not that kind.
At NASA, we have a tradition of handing out green papers, containing secret orders, during training.
極秘指令が書かれた
ミドリの紙が出されるのよ｡➡
それが通称｢グリーンカード｣｡
ダミアンには あらかじめ➡
They're known as green cards.
Damian received a green card that instructed him to hide the nozzle.
｢ノズルを隠しなさい｣っていう
グリーンカードが出されている｡➡
もちろん ヒビトは知らない⦆
Naturally, Hibito has no idea.
⦅仲間のミスによるストレスを
どうコントロールし➡
I can't find it.
It's a test to see how well you recover when someone else makes a mistake.
Hey, Damian...
不測の事態を
どう切り抜けるか…⦆
⦅それを鍛えるために チーム内で
極秘にﾄﾗﾌﾞﾙを起こさせるのが➡
Green cards are used to incite trouble within a team, which provides critical training.
｢グリーンカード｣ってわけ⦆
Green cards...
《グリーンカード…》
《間違いない｡グリーンカードだ》
That must be it... They're using green cards.
《極秘指令だから
福田さんは 誰にも話せない》
Fukuda can't tell us because it was a secret order.
《だとしたら アラーム音の
グリーンカードは…》
Which means that a green card about the alarm was sent to...
まだ おったんか｡
You're still awake?
なあ 正直者のやっさんに
１コ質問｡
Hey, I have a question for the very honest Ya.
Eh?
グリーンカード…もらった？
Did you receive a green card?
Ah!
Wh-What?
何？…なんでや！
正直にね｡
How?
Tell me the truth.
そ…それだけは
答えられへん…｡
I...
I can't do that...
That was the answer I needed.
《それが十分答えだよ》
さすが正直者｡
あ…ちょ～待て！
You just can't lie.
Hold on...
自分 なんで知ってんねん！
やっぱ時計は自分か!?
How did you know?
Did you break the clock?
違うよ～｡でも疑いは全部 晴れた｡
Nope.
But that answers any questions I had.
福田さん！
Fukuda...
よかった！
It's an honor.
⦅もし君が なぜ時計を壊したか➡
If you're able to figure out why I broke the clock,
その理由に気付いたら
その時は 握手でもしよう⦆
then when you do,
I'll shake your hand.
ありがとう｡
Thank you.
A Few Days Earlier
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](医師)
⦅目の疲れから頭痛になって
いませんか？➡
Any headaches from eye strain?
肩や腰はどうですか？⦆
Any back pain?
⦅いや～まだまだ大丈夫ですよ⦆
No, I'm still doing fine.
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](医師)⦅実は いい知らせが
あります➡
Actually, I have some good news for you.
古谷君からのプレゼント⦆
A present from Furuya.
⦅古谷君から？⦆
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](医師)⦅ですが その前に…⦆
From Furuya?
But first...
⦅あ…⦆
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](星加)⦅どうも福田さん➡
Hello, Fukuda.
あなたなら この選抜を
受けると思ってましたよ⦆
I knew you would make it
through the first two tests.
⦅星加君…か｡その声は⦆
Is that Hoshika's voice I hear?
⦅2008年の選抜を思い出すね～⦆
This reminds me of the 2008 selection...
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](星加)
⦅かつての戦友を監視する事に
なるとは➡
I never imagined that I'd have to monitor an old friend,
私も思ってませんでしたが
これも仕事です➡
but it's my job.
早速ですが 福田さん あなたに
グリーンカードが出ています⦆
I'll get to the point, Fukuda.
You will be receiving a green card.
⦅来たか⦆
So it begins.
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](星加)
⦅ご存知だと思いますが
グリーンカードのことや➡
I'm sure that you already know this very well,
but you cannot tell anyone about the green cards
あなたの指令については
他のメンバーに➡
or your particular set of orders.
一切 話しては なりません｡➡
いいですね？➡
Understood?
古谷君からのプレゼントと一緒に
パスボックスに入れてあります⦆
The card is in the pass-through box, along with the present from Furuya.
⦅あ～！⦆
"Orders.
Dismantle the clock thoroughly, so that it cannot be repaired.
⦅壊した時計を誰かが発見
できそうな場所に隠しなさい⦆
Hide the broken clock somewhere that it won't be found."
Why are you guys shaking hands for no reason?
なんやねん！いきなり握手して｡
気持ち悪っ！
That's creepy.
やっさん！俺は お前も
信じてるぜ！
Ya, I trust you.
はあ？やめろよ｡気持ち悪！
Huh?
Cut it out! You're scaring me!
(新田)おいおい お前ら！
Hey, guys...
そんなことよりアラームが
ないんだって！
I can't find the alarm!
なんや 自分｡クールなフリして➡
What's your problem?
You've been playing it cool.
実は寝る前に蚊とか発見したら
寝られへんタチやろ？
But if you spot a mosquito at bedtime, you can't sleep until it's dead.
何 言ってんだよ！寝れるよ！
That's bull!
I can sleep fine.
Don't worry about it. I can't sleep, either.
気にしなくても私も寝れないよ｡
いや 俺は寝れるって｡
No, I don't have any trouble sleeping.
俺なら蚊取り線香たくね｡
I'd use a bug zapper.
とにかく新田 これだけは
ハッキリ言えるよ｡
Anyway, Nitta...
There's one thing I do know.
この中には悪い奴は
１人もいない！
And that is...
There are no bad guys in this room!
それが わかっただけで 俺は
もう今日は ぐっすりだ｡
That's all I need
to sleep soundly tonight.
そうだ！とりあえず
応急処置なんですけど➡
I know.
As a temporary countermeasure,
みみせん
これで耳栓なんて
どうでしょう？
we can make earplugs.
こうやって くるくるっとして
ちょっと湿らせると➡
Twist the end like this...
Then you wet it a little.
さらに いい感じに｡
The result works pretty well.
お～！いいね！これ｡
Oh, this is nice!
まあまあやな｡
なるほど！これは
気がつかなかったな！
Not too shabby.
I see...
I never considered using earplugs.
《ちょっと聞こえるじゃねえか》
I can still hear them.
さ～寝よ！おやすみ～｡
Bedtime...
Good night!
(古谷)《これから毎日
鳴らさなアカンのか…》
Do I have to set off this alarm every night?
⦅指令｡本日から最終日まで 他の
メンバーが眠っている頃に➡
"Orders.
From now until the final day,
press the button on the remote control while the others are asleep.
アラームのリモコンスイッチを
押しなさい➡
アラームは１日最低
２０秒以上 鳴らしなさい⦆
The alarm must ring at least twenty seconds every day."
《でも なんでやろ｡
耳栓のおかげかな➡
Still, it's funny...
Maybe it's the earplugs.
明日は今日より
楽に押せそうや》
But I probably won't feel so bad when I press the button tomorrow.
《よかった…さっきのみんな
ちょっと元の空気に戻ってたし➡
This is great.
We're getting along like we used to.
そして何より我ながら
耳栓はナイスアイデア！》
And the earplugs were a brilliant idea, if I do say so myself!
《心おきなく いけるね！》
I can unleash the beast...
《う…うう…
やっぱり聞こえるじゃねえか》
The earplugs don't help at all.
Ａ班はグリーンカードの試練を
乗り越えたようですね｡
It appears Team A survived the green cards.
たいざい
月での長期滞在や火星までの
半年の旅➡
When preparing for extended lunar stays and Mars missions that require half-year voyages,
彼らに求められる
大きな資質として➡
it's important that astronauts be able to work as a team.
チームワークを保つ能力｡
そしてストレスに耐える力
ってのが重要だ｡
It's also important that they be able to endure stress.
(原田)なるほど｡
I see.
グリーンカードは その辺を
きわ
見極めるためには➡
Green cards are an effective way to evaluate those qualities.
効果的な手段なんだよ｡
そういうことだったんですか｡
So that's what they're for.
(星加)でも まさか南波君が
知ってたとはなあ｡➡
But I didn't expect that Nanba would be aware of their existence...
日々人君に聞いたのかな？
Perhaps Hibito told him.
まあ ストレスを
与えるのはね➡
Well, green cards aren't the only ways to cause stress, junior.
グリーンカードだけじゃないよ｡
新人君｡
窓のないバスも時間を伏せたのも
その他の細かい仕掛けも➡
The bus with no windows, destruction of the clocks,
and everything else we've been doing
あれは もう ぜ～んぶ ストレスを
かけるための作戦なんだよね｡
were all meant to evoke stress.
ぶあいそ
ツルミーのね 無愛想な顔も
ある意味 作戦なのよ｡➡
That includes Tsurumi's grumpy face.
ハハハ 今のツルミーに内緒ね｡
Don't tell Tsurumi I said that.
そして もうひとつ
｢２人を選べ｣と言ったこともだ｡
And there's another big one.
We told them to choose two members.
What?
(茄子田)あ いった いった｡
In! In!
おしい～！
So close!
やっぱりダメかな｡
This isn't going to work...
《自分の食事を抜いたりして
調整してみたけど》
I've tried to skip meals when it's my turn.
⦅いただきま～す⦆
Time for breakfast!
⦅あれ？せりかさんは？⦆
⦅ああ お先に どうぞ！⦆
Huh?
Aren't you going to eat, Serika?
Oh, it's okay. Go ahead and start.
⦅なんや 今日は量が少ないな｡
いや これが普通やな⦆
Oh, there's less to eat today.
Well, this is a normal-sized portion.
最終日までは もたない…｡
This won't last us until the final day.
《今のみんなの雰囲気なら
たぶん大丈夫！》
Everyone seems to be in a good mood, so it should be okay...
《食料が足りないことを
言うなら今しかない！》
This is the only chance I'll have to bring up the food shortage.
《そして言っても あんまり
怒らなそうな人に言おう！》
And I should go to someone who isn't likely to yell at me.
《となると》
Which means...
⦅なんやと～！⦆
What the hell?!
⦅メシがねえぞ～！⦆
There isn't enough food!
⦅うんうん⦆
I see.
せ～りかさん｡
Serika.
《こっちの２人…
どちらか》
I should talk to one of these two.
あれ？どうしたの？せりかさん｡
Huh?
What's wrong, Serika?
O-Okay...
《よし！》
あの…！
Um...
Huh?
う～ん｡そっか～足りないんだ｡
I see...
We're short on food.
ごめんなさい｡私のせいです｡
I'm sorry... It's my fault!
なんてこった…｡
This is terrible...
でも大丈夫｡
But don't worry.
Huh?
わかってる…わかってるよ～
せりかさん｡
I understand.
I understand perfectly, Serika!
《なにを!?》
Understand what?
《くっそ～ＪＡＸＡめ｡➡
Damn you, JAXA...
せりかさんにまで
グリーンカードを》
You gave Serika a green card
《食料不足になる指令を
出してたんだな｡ひどすぎる！》
that ordered her to cause a food shortage.
How evil.
せりかさん！
Serika...
どおりで大量に作ってると
思ってた！
This explains why you always made so much to eat.
《きびしい～！》
Uh-oh!
ご ごめんなさい！ホントに！
I-I'm so sorry!
いや～せりかさんが
謝ることはないって！
No, there's no reason for you to apologize.
悪いのはＪＡＸＡだ！
It's all JAXA's fault!
Huh?
(原田)出してないっスよね｡
グリーンカード｡
(星加)ないよ｡
You didn't give her a green card, did you?
Nope.
とにかく…➡
Anyway...
俺は せりかさんを信じてるよ｡
I trust you, Serika.
《なんだろう…これは》
What's going on?
《よくわかんないけど…》
I don't really understand...
《ま いっか》
But I guess it's all right.
《あ…ああ…》
《ああ…ああ…》
《ああ～ああ～ああ…あああ！》
《ああ～ああ～！》
うお～！なんだこりゃ！
急にキタ！
What's this?! There's a sudden spike!
星加さん 南波さんの
しんぱくすう
心拍数がヤバイんですけど！
Hoshika, Nanba's heartbeat is out of control!
だろうね…｡
Of course...
The lens inside my eyes
went completely out of focus when I saw you
The signs of love flooded the occipital lobe of my cerebrum
The words the left side of my brain produced
brought my vocal cords to reverberation
Vigorously my confession traversed my tongue
May I love you?
May I really love you?
May I be beside you? (The concentration of my hormones rose)
(Dopamine overwhelmed me)
Can I hold your hand? (My blood circulation powered up)
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#18 Ka-pe! Kenji!
＜閉鎖環境でのチームワークや➡
Green cards are used to test applicants' ability to work together and endure stress.
ストレスに耐える力を
見極めるためのグリーンカード＞
＜それが
ついに私にも やってきた＞
And now, I've received one!
What are you doing?
(古谷)＜お前 何しとんねん＞
＜南波さん!?＞
Nanba?!
Guys, I'm following orders from JAXA.
＜みんな！これは
ＪＡＸＡからの指示なんだ＞
＜一方 その頃 Ｂ班のケンジは
娘の風ちゃんを思い出していた＞
Meanwhile, Kenji, in Team B, thinks about his daughter, Fu.
What does Fuuka mean when she says "ka-pe"?
ふうか
＜風佳の言う｢かぺ｣って
どういう意味だ？＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Ka-pe! Kenji!"
So that's what it means...
＜そういうことか…｡
かぺるしかないな＞
I'll have to ka-pe my best.
パンパカパーン！
今週の宇宙写真です！
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
すっげえ！
誰？これ｡
Awesome!
Who are they?